Heath O'Brien, PhD Bioinformatician

May 2022

↑ 10 Marmaduke Street, Bristol BS3 4SQ, United Kingdom

hobrien.github.io

heath.obrien@gmail.com

heath_obrien

hobrien

Publications

in genome-informatics

About me —

I have 20 years of experience analyzing genetic data, both in academia and the private sector. I've worked on functional genomics, high-throughput sequencing and genotyping data from plants, fungi, bacteria and humans. I enjoy working on interdisciplinary projects and leading teams with diverse skill sets. I also have strong communication skills, having co-authored over 25 publications and presented my research at conferences in 7 countries.

Skills —

Functional genomics

Quantitative genetics

Microbiology

Data visualisation

Scientific communication

Project management

`

Python

BASH

AWS

SQL

Work History

2022-2022 Senior Bioinformatician

Sano Genetics

Developing pipelines to process generic data

2020-2022 Bioinformatician

Oxford UK

Cambridge UK

Theolytics

 Managing pipelines and compute architecture for genomic analyses of oncolytic viruses

 Advising on research strategy and on the design and analysis of experiments

Managing partnerships with other companies and academic scientists

2018-2020 Lead Bioinformatician

Frome, UK

Living DNA

 Leading a team of 6 bioinformaticians and data scientists developing methods to derive ancestry and health insights from genotyping data

 Working to secure external funding to develop novel genomic prediction approaches

 Collaboration with the engineering team to deploy processing pipelines at scale

2016-2018 Research Associate

Cardiff, UK

MRC Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics

 Differential gene expression and eQTL analyses on human brain samples

 Integration of functional genomic and large-scale population genetic datasets for schizophrenia and other neurophychiatric disorders

Organization of training seminars on data science (Rstudio, MySQL), version control (Git), and pipeline development (Snakemake, Bash)

• Deployment of results on the web using R-Shiny

2013-2016 Bioinformatician

Bristol, UK

University of Bristol

Comparative transcriptomics to determine the genetic basis of cell wall patterning responsible for colour-production in plant leaves

· Acting group leader for nine months

2008-2013 Postdoctoral Fellow

Toronto, ON, Canada

University of Toronto

• Comparative analyses of bacterial genomes

 Cloning of virulence factors and characterization using in-planta infection assays

2006-2008 Lab Administrator

Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

Oversight of Microbiology teaching labs

Managing lab technicians and teaching assistants

Education

2000-2006 PhD, Molecular systematics of cyanobacteria

Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

1994-1999 Bachelors degree, Plant Science

Edmonton, AB, Canada

University of Alberta

Training

Advanced Python for Biologists, PR Statistics, February, 2017. Advancing in R, PR Statistics, April, 2015.

Genetic Data Analysis, Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics, June, 2003.

References

Available on request.